Guide to the Fredericka Martin Papers ALBA.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fredericka Martin Papers
1923-2019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Martin, Fredericka I.
ALBA.001
45.54 Linear Feet in 39 record cartons, 7 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, 1 media box, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 folder in shared housing
25 audiocassettes
Fredericka (Freddie) Imogene Martin (1905-1992) was writer, photographer, historian, and chief nurse and administrator of the American medical volunteers who served during the Spanish Civil War. Following the war, Martin worked on the Pribilof Islands in the Bering Sea, becoming spokesperson and advocate for the indigenous Aleut sealing community. She produced a series of articles and books on Aleut culture and history and edited an Aleut language dictionary. In 1950, Martin moved to Cuernavaca, Mexico, a cultural outpost for Spanish exiles and American expatriates. During the 1960s, she initiated research for a projected book on the participation of the American medical units in the Spanish Civil War. Her papers reveal her dedication to amassing the most comprehensive record on the role of medical volunteers in Spain. In addition to the diaries, journals, clippings, leaflets and other ephemera donated to Martin, the collection includes extensive correspondence between Martin and hundreds of medical and combat veterans from around the world. Materials in this collection also document her writing career, anthropological interests, and life in Mexico.
Custodial History
The Fredericka Martin Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1991 by Martin's daughter Tobyanne Berenberg, and initially deposited at Brandeis University. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Berenberg donated additional materials to this collection in 2011, 2012, January 2015, January 2020, December 2023, and March 2024; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2011.115, 2012. 041, 2012.058, 2012.080, 2015.030, 2020.002, 2024.010, and 2024.023, respectively. In December 2021, additional folders were donated by Jessica Kraus; the accession number associated with this gift is 2021.090.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Fredericka (Freddie) Imogene Martin (1905-1992) was a writer, historian, and nurse who served as a chief nurse and medical administrator during the Spanish Civil War. Martin was born in Cooperstown, New York on June 2, 1905. Her father died in an accident before her birth and when she was five her mother remarried. They moved to Oneonta, New York where Martin -- a spirited child by her own account -- grew up in a warm and indulgent family. Following high school, she lived and worked with the St. Margaret Episcopalian Order of Nuns in Jersey City, New Jersey, and in 1925 attended the affiliated nursing school of Christ Hospital. She graduated with honors and as a young woman practiced professionally in hospitals throughout New York City. As supervisor and head nurse she served on the staffs of Bellevue, Fordham, Lying-In Hospital, and Crotona Park Hospital. In 1929, Martin married English-born Alexander Cohen. During the early 1930s Martin became an active member in the nurses union, attended political sciences classes at the Labor Temple in New York City, and began developing her aptitude for foreign languages, learning Russian and Yiddish. In 1935, while visiting her in-laws in England she traveled to Germany and Russia. Her time abroad awakened her to the growing threat of Fascism. When she returned, a nurses' union colleague encouraged Martin to become active in the then nascent Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy. Initially organized by a group of doctors and concerned citizens to provide medical supplies, food and clothing to the beleaguered Spanish Republic, by late 1936 the Medical Bureau was recruiting personnel to send to Spain as well.
On January 16, 1937 Martin embarked on the S.S. Paris as part of the first American medical unit to Spain. Under the leadership of surgeon Dr. Edward Barsky, Martin served as chief nurse and administrator of the American Hospital division. The first unit traveled with four ambulances, 12 tons of medical supplies and all the necessary equipment to outfit a 50-bed hospital. During her period of service, Martin supervised the work of fifty-four nurses, aided in the organization of six American hospitals on four fronts, and helped set up a mobile operating unit. She also organized literacy classes and trained Spanish women to assume some of the nursing and hospital administration duties. Her commanding bearing (at nearly 5'9" she was a full head taller than most of her staff), authoritative mien, and maternal attention to both the patients in the ward and the nurses under her management, earned her the affectionate appellation of "Ma."
In February 1938 Martin returned to the United States to conduct a yearlong national speaking tour, recruiting personnel and raising funds to keep the medical volunteers in Spain supplied. During the West Coast stretch of her tour Martin shared the stage with a representative of the Catalan government, and writer Dorothy Parker. Following her tour, Martin enrolled in the Public Administration program at New York University. Her studies were cut short when, in April 1939, she was invited to establish and serve as superintendent of a hospital in Greenbelt, Maryland -- a federally funded housing initiative created under the Resettlement Administration.
Martin's union with Cohen ended in an amicable divorce in the late 1930s and she married her second husband, Dr. Samuel Berenberg in 1940. In 1941 Berenberg took a medical assignment on the Pribilof Islands 300 miles off the coast of Alaska in the Bering Sea. With Martin's assistance, Berenberg managed the Fish and Wildlife Hospital on St. Paul Island. Martin's work brought her into contact with the indigenous Aleut sealing community, non-citizen wards of the U.S. Department of the Interior. Stirred by their struggle for self-determination and freedom from decades of discrimination and exploitation (first under the Russians and later the American government), Martin spent the next ten years of her life advocating on behalf of the community. She came to be regarded as an expert on the Aleut, producing a series of articles and books including The Hunting of the Silver Fleece, and Sea Bears: the Story of the Fur Seal, editing an Aleut language dictionary, and translating numerous manuscripts and articles.
With the bombing of Pearl Harbor, Martin and Berenberg returned to Greenbelt with their newborn daughter Tobyanne (named for Toby Jensky and Anne Taft, two nursing colleagues who had served with Martin in Spain). They settled in New York City where Berenberg became the chief of the Department of Health's Child Health Services and Martin embarked on her career as a writer. Following the dissolution of their marriage, Martin moved with the 9-year-old Tobyanne in 1950 to Cuernavaca, Mexico. A cultural outpost for Spanish exiles and American expatriates, Cuernavaca proved to be a congenial home for Martin. For the next 40 years she supported herself as translator, a travel book writer, and an instructor at a Spanish language institute, working with her former Medical Bureau colleague and fellow expatiate Lini (Fuhr) de Vries.
When Spanish Civil War combat veteran Arthur Landis published The Abraham Lincoln Brigade in 1967, Martin protested the lack of coverage given to the medical units and resolved to write a separate history on the Medical Bureau volunteers. In a letter to the Rabinowitz Foundation (08/20/1968) requesting funding for this project, Martin wrote:
"To tell the story of [American Medical Bureau] Field Units, their history must begin with the account of the organization and activities of the Medical Bureau in the US, the story of the Field Units at work in Spain, and their relationships and work with different nationalities and Spanish military and civilian organizations, and finally a summary of the contributions of AMB saving the lives of civilians and combatants."
When Spanish Civil War combat veteran Arthur Landis published The Abraham Lincoln Brigade in 1967, Martin protested the lack of coverage given to the medical units and resolved to write a separate history on the Medical Bureau volunteers. In a letter to the Rabinowitz Foundation (08/20/1968) requesting funding for this project, Martin wrote: To tell the story of [American Medical Bureau] Field Units, their history must begin with the account of the organization and activities of the Medical Bureau in the US, the story of the Field Units at work in Spain, and their relationships and work with different nationalities and Spanish military and civilian organizations, and finally a summary of the contributions of AMB saving the lives of civilians and combatants.This ambitious task would occupy her for the remainder of her life. Working chiefly from her home in Cuernavaca, Martin set out to amass the most comprehensive record on the role of the medical units in Spain. She enlisted the aid of former veterans, friends, librarians and archivists to obtain books and articles, locate missing volunteers, conduct research, and contribute primary materials and financial aid. She corresponded with hundreds of medical and combat veterans from around the world, sending questionnaires and accruing personal data. In the early 1970s she traveled through Europe, Israel and the United States meeting with former Medical Bureau colleagues, conducting interviews, visiting research repositories, and collecting memorabilia and materials for her history. She traveled to Spain in 1972 to conduct research and revisited Villa Paz, the lavish estate that during the war had served as a front-line hospital.
Although Martin produced abundant notes and drafted several chapters, struggles with money, poor clerical assistance, and failing health hampered her in her efforts to complete her Medical Bureau history. By 1982 her attention turned from her writing project to finding a suitable repository to administer the materials she had so assiduously collected and maintained in her cramped Cuernavaca cottage. In 1986, in recognition for her contributions to the Aleut, Martin was made honorary lifetime citizen of St. Paul Island, and was awarded an honorary doctorate by the University of Alaska. On October 4, 1992 Martin died in Cuernavaca. She was 87 years old.
Scope and Contents
The Fredericka Martin Papers (dated 1926-2019) contains materials created and collected by Martin both during and after her medical aid services in Spain during the Spanish Civil War. Materials include correspondence, questionnaires, diaries, journals, personal essays, newspaper clippings, artifacts, published materials, and leaflets and other ephemera documenting Martin's personal research; the experiences of combat volunteers, especially their lives as veterans; and the work of various medical units from the International Brigade, including the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy. This collection also contains personal correspondence with researchers, political figures, and other friends. In addition to materials concerning her experiences in the Spanish Civil War, this collection also documents Martin's personal life, her immigration to Mexico, and her career as a writer through correspondence, ephemera, newspaper clippings, and manuscripts in various stages.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into ten series.
Series I is arranged alphabetically by country and within each country by personal name. Series II, III, and V are arranged alphabetically. Series IV is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with unidentified incoming and outgoing correspondence arranged at the end of the series. See Scope and Content Note regarding the arrangement of Series VII. Series VIII-X have not been arranged by an archivist.
Series I. Medical Personnel: Biographical Files and Correspondence, 1936-1988
Series II. Medical Subject Files, 1937-1987
Series III. Combat Volunteers: Biographical Files and Correspondence, 1937-1987
Series IV. General Correspondence, 1937-1985
Series V. General Subject Files, 1937-1990
Series VI. Artifacts: Textiles and Pin, 1937
Series VII. Duplicates, 1936-1984
Series VIII: Unprocessed Materials
Series IX. 2015 Accretion
Series X. 2020 Accretion
Series XI. 2021 Accretion
Series XII. 2024 Accretion
Related Materials
Fredericka Martin Photograph Collection (ALBA PHOTO 001)
Fredericka Martin. University of Alaska Fairbanks, Rasmuson Library, Oral History Collection (H86-118; H90-10-11)
Fredericka Martin Papers. Nettie Lee Benson Latin American Collection. The University of Texas at Austin
Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter Papers (ALBA 055)
Edward K. Barsky Papers (ALBA 125)
Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131)
Separated Materials
Photographs were separated from Fredericka Martin's manuscript materials in the course of processing and established as a separate collection, the Fredericka Martin Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 001).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by TobyAnne Berenberg in 1991, with further accretions in 2011-2025.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Barcelona (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Medical care.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Sources; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- African Americans; Drafts (documents); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Biography; Political prisoners -- Spain; Biography files.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Children; Personal papers.; Correspondence.; Madrid (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Literature and the war.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Pribilof Islands (Alaska).; Articles.; Cuernavaca (Mexico); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Foreign public opinion; Research (document genres).; Raven, Robert.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Wolff, Milton.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Vanzant, Frances; Weissman, Irving, 1905-; Southworth, Herbert Rutledge; Taft, Anne, 1912-1990; Sherman, John; Smith, Randall, 1917-1989; Rosenstone, Robert A.; Ryan, William G.; American Rescue Ship Mission; American Relief Ship for Spain; Zlatovski, George.; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Wyden, Peter; Echeveria, Soule; Eloesser, Leo; Dhago, Joseph; De Vries, Lini M.; Buck, Tim, 1891-1973; Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee; Bruzzichesi, Ave; Bingham de Urquidi, Mary; Berenberg, Samuel R.; Robbin, Violet; Reissig, Herman F.; Rauschwald, Mark, 1908-1985; Orr, H. Winnett (Hiram Winnett), 1877-1956; O'Reilly, John Patrick; Oram, Harold L., 1907-1990; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Maas, Johana; Loeb, James I. (James Isaac), 1908-; Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986; Miller, Louis; Medem, Gina; Matthews, Herbert Lionel, 1900-1977; Ahrend Kirkpatrick, Evelyn; Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975; Lending, Edward Isaac, 1912-2003; Beeching, William; Berch, Victor A.; Jensky, Toby, 1911-1995; Jackson, Gabriel; Freeman, Helen; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Milward Barnett, Monica; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Spanish Medical Aid Committee (England)
- Series I: Medical Personnel: Biographical Files and Correspondence, 1936-1988
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I. Medical Personnel: Biographical Files and Correspondence 1936-1988. This series includes correspondence from and biographical material on hundreds of medical volunteers from over 25 countries (Includes materials written in Spanish, French, Russian, Rumanian and German). Particularly informative are questionnaires sent by Martin and filled in by dozens of doctors, nurses, ambulance drives and other medical personnel detailing their activities in Spain and their subsequent experiences. These also provide data on political affiliations before and after the war and personal motivations for going to Spain. Much of the correspondence to and from Martin chronicles the later lives of the volunteers and offers insights to the range of attitudes regarding Martin's efforts to record their work in Spain. Additionally, this series contains materials donated to Martin, including Spanish Civil War letters (originals and copies), diaries and journals (typescripts and photocopies) personal essays, clippings, leaflets, and other ephemera. Martin also collected medical writings and other materials published by the medical volunteers.
  Notable in this series are: English volunteer Monica Milward Barnett's diary (transcription), which provides information on the Spanish Medical Aid Committee office in Barcelona; John Patrick O'Reilly's handwritten ward instructions from Villa Paz; a typescript in English of Mary Bingham de Urquidi's "Mercy in Madrid: a Personal History of the Spanish Civil War" (published in Spanish in 1975 under the title Misericordia en Madrid, an English-language version has never appeared in print); recollections of Dutch nurse Johana Maas; letters written by Ave Bruzzichesi to Dr. Leo Eloesser describing the withdrawal of foreign units from Spain, as well as files on Dr. Eloesser which include dispatches to the Medical Bureau from Spain; Spanish Civil War documents and Medical Bureau ephemera from Jose Dhaga, a native of Peru who volunteered with the North American medical unit; correspondence and material related to Alba Novac and her husband William Ryan, a combat volunteer who appeared before HUAC as a cooperative witness; files on Frances Vanzant, the only woman doctor attached to the American unit; information on George Zlatovski, charged in 1957 with spying for the Soviet Union; and Helen Freeman's 1949 letters, written from Germany while working for the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee.
  Letters to and from Martin's close friends Anne Taft Muldavin and Toby Jensky offer insights on Martin's life and work over a forty-year period. This series also contains a biographical file on Martin, notes she took on her return to Spain in 1972, and a hospital ward journal she kept in Spain during the war. Research progress reports and rough drafts of Martin's manuscript "Proud within Themselves" (her unfinished history of the medical units) can be found here.
  - Albania: General Correspondence and Research, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albania: Shkupi, Justina, undated, 1959, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Argentina: General Correspondence and Research, 1936, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Argentina: Bermann, Gergorio, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Argentina: Colmeyna, Hector, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Argentina: Ostrovsky, David, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Australia: General Correspondence and Research, undated, 1948, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Australia: Hodgson, Agnes, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Australia: Holman, Portia, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Australia: Lawson, Mary, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Australia: MacFarlane, May, 1939, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Australia: Miller, Margot, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Australia: Odgers, Esme, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Australia: Palmer, Aileen, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Australia: Wilson, Una, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Austria: Doctors and Nurses, undated, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Austria: Amann, Ernesto and Ursula Mayer Amann, 1957-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Austria: Brauner, Alfred and Francoise, 1970-1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Austria: Dürmeyer, René, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Austria: Edel, Emmanuel, undated, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Austria: Endler, Nathan (a.k.a. Hermann), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Austria: Fischer, Walter (a.k.a. Alexander Langer), 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Austria: Freudmann, Walter, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Austria: Heller, Walter, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Austria: Jensen, Fritz (a.k.a. Friedrich Albert Jerusalem), 1939, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Austria: Langer, Maximilian and Maria Lisbeth Glas Langer (a.k.a. Mimi Mandovi), undated, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Austria: Perelmann, Anja Hammermann and Michel Perelmann, undated, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Austria: Stridsberg, Augusta Franziska (a.k.a. Gusti Jirku), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Toch, Josef (includes copies of letter from FM to JT and wife, Justi)), 1971-1984 (Box 1, Folder 28A)
  - Belgium: General Correspondence and Research, undated, 1938, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Belgium: Corman, Matthieu (Journalist covering the hospital at Onteniente), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Belgium: Delvigne, Jean, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Belgium: Dumont, René, undated, 1939, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Belgium: Korn, Anna and Adele Korn Szerman, undated, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Belgium: Lowenthal, [?], 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Belgium: Marteaux, Albert, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Brazil: Mira López, Emilio: "Psychological Effects of War" (Lecture), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bulgaria: General Correspondence and Research, undated, 1942, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Bulgaria: Nurses, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bulgaria: Angeluscheff, Zhivko D., undated, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bulgaria: Canetti, Ianto Davidov, undated, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bulgaria: Grozev, Dimitar Simeonov, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Bulgaria: Kolarov, Peter Vasilev (a.k.a. Yaroslav Franek), undated, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Bulgaria: Kristanov, Tsventan (a.k.a. Oscar Telge), undated, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bulgaria: Kristanov, Tsventan (a.k.a. Oscar Telge): Medical Services of the International Brigades(photocopy), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bulgaria: Kristanov, Tsventan (a.k.a. Oscar Telge): Memoirs, excerpt, [1967] (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Bulgaria: Kristanov, Tsventan (a.k.a. Oscar Telge): Memoirs (Martin's notes), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Bulgaria: Kristanov, Tsventan (a.k.a. Oscar Telge): Writings, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Bulgaria: Michev, Konstantin, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Canada: General Correspondence, 1938, 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Canada: Doctors, Nurses, Ambulance Drivers, undated, 1937, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Canada: Abramson, Samuel H. (Ambulance Driver), undated, 1938, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Canada: Bethune, Norman: Articles and Clippings, 1937, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Canada: Bethune, Norman: Correspondence with Roderick Stewart (Bethune biographer), 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Canada: Bethune, Norman: Research Notes and Materials, undated, 1936, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Canada: Bethune, Norman: Writings, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Canada: Hamilton, Robert (a.k.a. Robert Bell), 1937-1938, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Canada: Lawson, Jean Watt, 1970-1983 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Canada: Pike, Florence (a.k.a. Florence Mildred Tew), 1936-1940, 1968-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Canada: Sollenberg, Randall, undated, 1938, 1970-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chile: Research Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cuba: Doctors and Nurses, undated, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)